I want to tell you
أريد أن أخبركم
how 20,000 remarkable young people
كيف انتهي المطاف ب 20 ألف شاب رائعين
from over 100 countries
من حوالي 100 دولة
ended up in Cuba
في كوبا
and are transforming health in their communities.
و الآن يغيرون الرعاية الصحية في مجتمعاتهم.
Ninety percent of them would never
تسعون بالمائة منهم لم يكونوا
have left home at all
ليتركوا وطنهم ابداً
if it weren't for a scholarship to study medicine in Cuba
لولا المنحة لدراسة الطب في كوبا
and a commitment to go back
و التعهد بالعودة
to places like the ones they'd come from —
لأماكن مثل التي أتوا منها
remote farmlands, mountains, ghettos —
مزارع بعيدة و جبال و أحياء فقيرة
to become doctors for people like themselves,
ليصبحوا أطباء لأشخاص مثلهم
to walk the walk.
لنمشي الدرب.
Havana's Latin American Medical School:
كلية هافانا الأمريكية اللاتينية للطب:
It's the largest medical school in the world,
إنها أكبر كلية طب في العالم
graduating 23,000 young doctors
خرجت 23 ألف طبيب شاب
since its first class of 2005,
منذ أول فصل لها في 2005،
with nearly 10,000 more in the pipeline.
مع أكثر من 10 آلاف طالب في الدراسة.
Its mission, to train physicians for the people
مهمتها تدريب أطباء للناس
who need them the most:
الذين يحتاجونهم أكثر من أي شيء آخر:
the over one billion
الأكثر من مليار
who have never seen a doctor,
الذين لم يروا طبيباً من قبل،
the people who live and die
الناس التي تعيش و تموت
under every poverty line ever invented.
تحت كل خطوط الفقر التي وجدت.
Its students defy all norms.
طلابها يتحدون كل المعايير.
They're the school's biggest risk
هم أكبر مجازفات الكلية
and also its best bet.
و أيضا أفضل رهان لها.
They're recruited from the poorest,
يتم تجنيدهم من أفقر
most broken places on our planet
و أكثرالأماكن تحطماً في العالم
by a school that believes they can become
بواسطة الكلية التي تؤمن أنهم يستطيعون أن يصبحوا
not just the good
ليس فقط أطباء جيدين
but the excellent physicians
بل الأطباء الأكثر تميزاً
their communities desperately need,
الذين تحتاجهم مجتمعاتهم بشدة،
that they will practice where most doctors don't,
إنهم سيتدربون في أماكن لا يعمل فيها معظم الأطباء،
in places not only poor
في أماكن ليست فقيرة فحسب
but oftentimes dangerous,
بل و كثير من الأحيان خطيرة،
carrying venom antidotes in their backpacks
يحملون ترياق السم في حقائبهم
or navigating neighborhoods
أو يتنقلون في الحارات
riddled by drugs, gangs and bullets,
التي مزقتها المخدرات أو العصابات أو الرصاصات،
their home ground.
أرض وطنهم.
The hope is that they will help
الأمل أنهم سيساعدون
transform access to care,
في تغيير مستوى الحصول علي الرعاية،
the health picture in impoverished areas,
صورة الرعاية الصحية في المناطق الفقيرة،
and even the way medicine itself
و حتي طريقة الطب
is learned and practiced,
من حيث الدراسة و التدريب،
and that they will become pioneers in our global reach
و أنهم سيكونون رواداً في نطاقنا العالمي
for universal health coverage,
للتغطية العالمية للصحة،
surely a tall order.
هي بالطبع مهمة صعبة.
Two big storms and this notion of "walk the walk"
إعصاران كبيران و فكرة "مشي الدرب"
prompted creation of ELAM back in 1998.
كانت سبباً في إنشاء ELAM في 1998.
The Hurricanes Georges and Mitch
الإعصاران جورج و ميتش
had ripped through the Caribbean
اجتاحا جزر الكاريبي
and Central America,
و أمريكا الوسطى،
leaving 30,000 dead
مخلفة 30 ألف حالة وفاة
and two and a half million homeless.
و 2 و نصف مليون متشرد.
Hundreds of Cuban doctors volunteered for disaster response,
المئات من الأطباء الكوبيين تطوعوا للاستجابة للكارثة،
but when they got there,
لكن عندما وصلوا،
they found a bigger disaster:
وجدوا كارثة أكبر:
whole communities with no healthcare,
مجتمعات كاملة بلا رعاية طبية،
doors bolted shut on rural hospitals
أبواب المستشفيات الريفية مغلقة
for lack of staff,
لنقص الموظفين،
and just too many babies dying
و الكثير من الأطفال تموت
before their first birthday.
قبل أول عيد ميلاد لهم
What would happen when these Cuban doctors left?
ماذا سيحدث عندما يغادر هؤلاء الاطباء الكوبيين؟
New doctors were needed to make care sustainable,
يجب أن يظهر أطباء جدد لتبقي الرعاية مستدامة،
but where would they come from?
و لكن من أين سيأتوا؟
Where would they train?
أين سيتم تدريبهم؟
In Havana, the campus of a former naval academy
في هافانا، الحرم الجامعي للأكاديمية البحرية سابقاً
was turned over to the Cuban Health Ministry
تم تسليمه لوزارة الصحة الكوبية
to become the Latin American Medical School,
ليصبح الكلية الطبية الامريكية اللاتينية،
ELAM.
ELAM.
were offered to hundreds of students
كانت تقدم للمئات من الطلبة
from the countries hardest hit by the storms.
من البلدان الأشد تضرراً من العواصف.
As a journalist in Havana,
كصحفية في هافانا،
I watched the first 97 Nicaraguans arrive
شاهدت وصول أول 97 طالب من نيكاراجوا
in March 1999,
في مارس 1999،
settling into dorms barely refurbished
سكنوا في مساكن الطلبة بالكاد تم ترميمها
and helping their professors not only sweep out the classrooms
و ساعدوا أساتذتهم ليس فقط في كنس الفصول
but move in the desks and the chairs and the microscopes.
بل أيضا حركوا المناضد و المقاعد و الميكروسكوبات.
Over the next few years,
و خلال السنين القليلة التالية،
governments throughout the Americas
الحكومات في القاراتين الأمريكتين
requested scholarships for their own students,
طلبت منحاً دراسية لطلابها
and the Congressional Black Caucus
و كتلة النواب السود بالكونغرس
asked for and received hundreds of scholarships
طالبوا و حصلوا علي المئات من المنح الدراسية
for young people from the USA.
للشباب من الولايات المتحدة الامريكية،
Today, among the 23,000
اليوم, بين 23 ألف
are graduates from 83 countries
هناك خريجين من 83 دولة
in the Americas, Africa and Asia,
من الأمريكتين و أفريقيا و آسيا،
and enrollment has grown to 123 nations.
كما زاد التسجيل ليصل إلي 123 دولة.
More than half the students are young women.
أكثر من نصف الطلبة من النساء الشابات.
They come from 100 ethnic groups,
أتوا من أكثر من 100 مجموعة عرقية،
speak 50 different languages.
يتكلمون 50 لغة مختلفة.
WHO Director Margaret Chan said,
مديرة منظمة الصحة العالمية مارجريت شان قالت،
"For once, if you are poor, female,
"لمرة, لو كنتَ فقيراً أو أنثي
or from an indigenous population,
أو من السكان الأصليين،
you have a distinct advantage,
فإن لك ميزة واضحة،
an ethic that makes this medical school unique."
أخلاقيات تجعل هذه المدرسة الطبية مميزة."
Luther Castillo comes from San Pedro de Tocamacho
لوثر كاستلو أتي من سان بيدرو دي توكامتشو
on the Atlantic coast of Honduras.
علي الشاطئ الأطلنطي لبلد الهندوراس.
There's no running water,
لا يوجد مياه جارية،
no electricity there,
و لا كهرباء هناك،
and to reach the village, you have to walk for hours
و لتصل إلى القرية، عليك أن تمشي لساعات
or take your chances in a pickup truck like I did
أو تجرب حظك بركوب عربة نقل كما فعلت أنا
skirting the waves of the Atlantic.
تتجنب أمواج المحيط الأطلنطي.
Luther was one of 40 Tocamacho children
لوثر كان واحداً من 40 طفل من توكاماتشو
who started grammar school,
الذين بدأوا المدرسة الاعدادية،
the sons and daughters of a black indigenous people
أبناء و بنات السكان السود الأصليين
known as the Garífuna,
المعروفين باسم الجاريفونا،
20 percent of the Honduran population.
و يمثلون 20 بالمائة من سكان هندوراس.
The nearest healthcare was fatal miles away.
إن أقرب رعاية صحية كانت بعيدة بأميال على نحو مميت.
Luther had to walk three hours every day
كان لوثر يسير 3 ساعات كل يوم
to middle school.
إلى المدرسة الاعدادية.
Only 17 made that trip.
قام 17 فقط بهذه الرحلة
Only five went on to high school,
وصل 5 فقط للمدرسة الثانوية،
and only one to university:
و واحد فقط وصل للجامعة:
Luther, to ELAM,
لوثر, وصل لـ ELAM،
among the first crop of Garífuna graduates.
ضمن أول مجموعة من خريجي جرافينا.
Just two Garífuna doctors had preceded them
طبيبين فقط من جرافينا سبقوهم
in all of Honduran history.
على مدار تاريخ الهندوراس.
Now there are 69, thanks to ELAM.
هناك الآن 69، بفضل ELAM.
Big problems need big solutions,
إن المشاكل الكبري تحتاج لحلول كبرى،
sparked by big ideas, imagination and audacity,
ملهمة بأفكار كبيرة و خيال وجرأة،
but also solutions that work.
لكن أيضاً بحلول مجدية.
ELAM's faculty had no handy evidence base
لا تمتلك كلية ELAM قاعدة أدلة مفيدة
to guide them, so they learned the hard way,
لإرشادهم, لذلك تعلموا بالطريقة الصعبة،
by doing and correcting course as they went.
عن طريق العمل ثم تصحيح المقررات كلما درسوها.
Even the brightest students
حتي ألمع الطلبة
from these poor communities
من أفقر المجتمعات هذه
weren't academically prepared
لم يكونوا جاهزين أكاديمياً
for six years of medical training,
لست سنوات من دراسة الطب،
so a bridging course was set up in sciences.
لذلك تم وضع دروة تكميلية في العلوم.
Then came language:
ثم أتت اللغة:
these were Mapuche, Quechuas, Guaraní, Garífuna,
لقد كانوا من شعوب مابوتشي و كويتشاس و جواراني و جاريفونا
indigenous peoples
سكان أصليين
who learned Spanish as a second language,
درسوا اللغة الإسبانية كلغة ثانية،
or Haitians who spoke Creole.
أو هايتين و الذين تكلموا لغة الكريول.
So Spanish became part
لذلك فإن الإسبانية أصبحت جزءاً
of the pre-pre-med curriculum.
من مناهج قبل الاعداد للطب.
Even so, in Cuba,
وحتى مع ذلك، في كوبا
the music, the food, the smells,
الموسيقي، الطعام و الروائح،
just about everything was different,
كل شئ كان مختلفاً،
so faculty became family, ELAM home.
لذا أصبحت الكلية بمثابة الأسرة و أصبحت ELAM بمثابة البيت.
Religions ranged from indigenous beliefs
الأديان تراوحت من معتقدات السكان الأصليين
to Yoruba, Muslim and Christian evangelical.
إلي ديانة اليوروبا و المسلمين و المسيحين الإنجيليين.
Embracing diversity became a way of life.
إن احتضان التنوع أصبح طريقة حياة.
Why have so many countries
لماذا كل هذه الدول
asked for these scholarships?
طلبت هذه المنحة الدراسية؟
First, they just don't have enough doctors,
أولاً, هم فقط لا يملكون أطباء بما فيه الكفاية،
and where they do, their distribution
و حيثما وجدوا، فإن توزيعهم يكون
is skewed against the poor,
منحازاً ضد الفقراء،
because our global health crisis
لأن أزمتنا الصحية العالمية
is fed by a crisis in human resources.
سببها الأساسي أزمة في الموارد البشرية.
We are short four to seven million health workers
ينقصنا 4 إلي 7 مليون عامل في الرعاية الصحية
just to meet basic needs,
فقط لتلبية المتطلبات الأساسية،
and the problem is everywhere.
و المشكلة في كل مكان.
Doctors are concentrated in the cities,
الأطباء متمركزون في المدن،
where only half the world's people live,
حيث يسكن نصف سكان العالم فحسب،
and within cities,
و في داخل المدن،
not in the shantytowns or South L.A.
ليس في منطقة البيوت الصفيح أو جنوب لوس أنجلوس.
Here in the United States,
هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
where we have healthcare reform,
حيث نقوم بإصلاح نظام الرعاية الصحية،
we don't have the professionals we need.
لا نملك المحترفين الذين نحتاجهم.
By 2020, we will be short
بحلول 2020، سينقصنا
45,000 primary care physicians.
45 ألف من أطباء الرعاية الصحية الأولية.
And we're also part of the problem.
و نحن أيضاً جزء من المشكلة.
The United States is the number one importer
الولايات المتحدة هي المستورد الأول
of doctors from developing countries.
للأطباء من الدول النامية.
The second reasons students flock to Cuba
السبب الثاني لاحتشاد الطلبة في كوبا
is the island's own health report card,
هو بطاقة التقرير الصحي الخاصة بالجزيرة،
relying on strong primary care.
المعتمدة علي رعاية صحية أولية قوية.
A commission from The Lancet
لجنة من جريدة لانسيت (المشرط) الطبية
rates Cuba among the best performing
قيمت كوبا ضمن أفضل أداء
middle-income countries in health.
للدول متوسطة الدخل في الرعاية الصحية.
Save the Children ranks Cuba
منظمة "أنقذوا الاطفال" تقيم كوبا
the best country in Latin America to become a mother.
كأفضل دولة في أمريكا اللاتينية لتصبحي أماً فيها.
Cuba has similar life expectancy
لدى كوبا متوسط عمر متوقع للأفراد مثل الولايات المتحدة
and lower infant mortality than the United States,
وأقل نسبة وفيات للرضع عن الولايات المتحدة،
with fewer disparities,
مع فوارق أقل،
while spending per person
بينما إنفاق الفرد الواحد
one 20th of what we do on health
جزء من عشرين مما ينفق علي الرعاية الصحية
here in the USA.
هنا في الولايات المتحدة.
Academically, ELAM is tough,
أكاديميا, ELAM صعبة،
but 80 percent of its students graduate.
لكن 80 بالمائة من طلابها يتخرجون.
The subjects are familiar —
المواد الدراسية هي المألوفة في الطب -
basic and clinical sciences —
الأساسيات و العلوم الطبية -
but there are major differences.
لكن هناك فروق رئيسية.
First, training has moved out of the ivory tower
أولاً انتقل التدريب من الأبراج العاجية
and into clinic classrooms and neighborhoods,
إلي العيادات الدراسية و الحارات،
the kinds of places most of these grads will practice.
الأماكن التي سيتمرن فيها أغلب هؤلاء الخريجين.
Sure, they have lectures and hospital rotations too,
بالتأكيد، يحضرون محاضرات و يناوبون في المستشفيات ايضاً،
but community-based learning starts on day one.
لكن التعليم المعتمد علي المجتمع يبدأ من اليوم الأول.
Second, students treat the whole patient,
ثانياً، الطلبة يعالجون المريض كله،
mind and body,
عقلاً و جسداً،
in the context of their families, their communities
في سياق عائلاتهم و مجتمعاتهم
and their culture.
و ثقافاتهم.
Third, they learn public health:
ثالثاً، يتعلمون الصحة العامة:
to assess their patients' drinking water, housing,
لتقييم مياه الشرب لمرضاهم و كذلك السكن
social and economic conditions.
و الظروف الاجتماعية و الإقتصادية.
Fourth, they are taught
رابعاً، يتم تعليمهم
that a good patient interview
أن المحادثة الجيدة للمريض
and a thorough clinical exam
و الفحص الطبي الشامل
provide most of the clues for diagnosis,
يقدم كل المفاتيح للتشخيص،
saving costly technology for confirmation.
مما يوفر التأكيدات التكنولوجية المكلفة.
And finally, they're taught over and over again
و أخيراً، يتعلمون و يتعلمون
the importance of prevention,
أهمية الوقاية،
especially as chronic diseases
خاصة الأمراض المزمنة
cripple health systems worldwide.
التي تشل النظام الصحي في كل العالم.
Such an in-service learning
مثل هذا النوع من التعليم
also comes with a team approach,
أيضاً يرافقه نهج الفريق،
as much how to work in teams
كما في العمل في فريق
as how to lead them,
كما كيف تقودهم،
with a dose of humility.
مع جرعة من التواضع.
Upon graduation, these doctors share
عند التخرج، يتشارك هؤلاء الأطباء
their knowledge with nurse's aids, midwives,
معرفتهم مع مساعدات الممرضات والقابلات
community health workers,
و العاملين بالرعاية الصحية،
to help them become better at what they do,
ليساعدوهم ليصبحوا أفضل في ما يفعلونه،
not to replace them,
و ليس لاستبدالهم،
to work with shamans and traditional healers.
للعمل مع المعالجين بالسحر و العلاج التقليدي.
ELAM's graduates:
خريجو ELAM،
Are they proving this audacious experiment right?
هل يثبتون أن تجربة الجرأة صحيحة ؟
Dozens of projects give us an inkling
العشرات من المشاريع تعطينا تلميحات
of what they're capable of doing.
لما يستطيعون فعله.
Take the Garífuna grads.
خذ علي سبيل المثال خريجي الجرافينا.
They not only went to work back home,
ليس فقط عادوا للعمل في وطنهم،
but they organized their communities to build
بل نظموا مجتمعاتهم لبناء
Honduras' first indigenous hospital.
أول مشفي للسكان الاصليين في الهندوراس.
With an architect's help,
بمساعدة معماري،
residents literally raised it from the ground up.
أقامها السكان حرفيا من الأرض حتي الأعلي.
The first patients walked through the doors
دخل أوائل المرضى من الأبواب
in December 2007,
في ديسمبر 2007،
and since then, the hospital has received
و من وقتها استقبلت المستشفي
nearly one million patient visits.
ما يقرب من مليون زيارة.
And government is paying attention,
و الحكومة تولي اهتماماً للموضوع،
upholding the hospital as a model
تدعم المستشفي لتكون مثال
of rural public health for Honduras.
للرعاية الصحية الريفية في الهندوراس.
ELAM's graduates are smart,
خريجو ELAM أذكياء
strong and also dedicated.
أقوياء و مخلصون.
Haiti, January 2010.
هاييتي، يناير 2010.
The pain.
الألم،
People buried under 30 million tons of rubble.
الناس مدفونين تحت 30 مليون طن من الأنقاض.
Overwhelming.
مربك للمشاعر.
Three hundred forty Cuban doctors
340 طبيب كوبي
were already on the ground long term.
كانوا بالفعل هناك لفترة طويلة.
More were on their way. Many more were needed.
و المزيد كانوا في طريقهم. و المزيد كانوا مطلوبين.
At ELAM, students worked round the clock
في ELAM، عمل الطلبة طوال الوقت
to contact 2,000 graduates.
للتواصل مع 2000 خريج.
As a result, hundreds arrived in Haiti,
كنتيجة لذلك، وصل المئات لهاييتي،
27 countries' worth, from Mali in the Sahara
ما يساوي 27 دولة، من مالي في الصحراء الكبري
to St. Lucia, Bolivia, Chile and the USA.
إلى سانت لوسيا و بوليفيا و تشيلي و الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
They spoke easily to each other in Spanish
تكلموا بسهولة ليصلوا للآخرين بالإسبانية
and listened to their patients in Creole
و استمعوا لمرضاهم باللغة الكريولية
thanks to Haitian medical students
بفضل طلاب طب هايتيون
flown in from ELAM in Cuba.
سافروا من ELAM لكوبا.
Many stayed for months,
بقي العديد منهم لشهور،
Hundreds of Haitian graduates
المئات من خريجي هايتي
had to pick up the pieces,
كان عليهم إصلاح ما فسد،
overcome their own heartbreak,
أن يتخطوا انفطار قلوبهم،
and then pick up the burden
و أن يحملوا عبء
of building a new public health system for Haiti.
بناء نظام رعاية صحية جديد في هايتي.
Today, with aid of organizations and governments
اليوم، و بمساعدة المنظمات و الحكومات
from Norway to Cuba to Brazil,
من النرويج لكوبا للبرازيل،
dozens of new health centers have been built,
بنيت العشرات من مراكز الصحة
by ELAM graduates.
ترأسها خريجو ELAM.
Yet the Haitian story
مع ذلك فإن تاريخ هاييتي
also illustrates some of the bigger problems
أيضاً يبين بعض المشاكل الأكبر
faced in many countries.
التي تواجه دولاً عديدة.
Take a look:
لنلقي نظرة:
748 Haitian graduates by 2012, when cholera struck,
748 هايتي تخرجوا في 2012، عندما حلّت الكوليرا،
nearly half working in the public health sector
تقريبا نصفهم عملوا في قسم الصحة العامة
but one quarter unemployed,
لكن ربعهم عاطلين عن العمل،
and 110 had left Haiti altogether.
و 110 غادروا هاييتي تماماً.
So in the best case scenarios,
لذا في أفضل السناريوهات،
these graduates are staffing
هؤلاء الخريجين يتم توظيفهم
and thus strengthening public health systems,
وبالتالي يقوون نظام الصحة العامة،
where often they're the only doctors around.
حيث غالباً ما يكونون الأطباء الوحيدين في المكان.
In the worst cases, there are simply not enough jobs
في أسوء الحالات، ببساطة لا يوجد عمل كاف
in the public health sector,
في قسم الصحة العامة،
where most poor people are treated,
حيث يتم علاج معظم الناس،
not enough political will, not enough resources,
نية سياسية غير كافية و موارد غير كافية،
not enough anything —
لا شيء كافٍ -
just too many patients with no care.
فقط مرضي كثر بلا رعاية.
The grads face pressure from their families too,
يواجه الخريجون ضغط من عائلاتهم أيضاً،
desperate to make ends meet,
بيأس لتغطية نفقاتهم،
so when there are no public sector jobs,
لذلك عندما لا يوجد أعمال في القطاع العام،
these new MDs decamp into private practice,
يتحول هؤلاء الأطباء للعمل الخاص،
or go abroad to send money home.
أو يسافروا ليرسلوا المال لبلادهم.
Worst of all, in some countries,
و أسوء من كل شيء، في بعض البلاد
medical societies influence accreditation bodies
تؤثر المجتمعات الطبية على هيئات الاعتماد
not to honor the ELAM degree,
كي لا تمجد لدرجة ELAM،
fearful these grads will take their jobs
خوفاً من أن يأخذ هؤلاء الخريجين وظائفهم
or reduce their patient loads and income.
أو يقللوا من أعداد مرضاهم و دخلهم.
It's not a question of competencies.
إنها ليست مسألة تنافس.
Here in the USA, the California Medical Board
هنا في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية، المجلس الطبي في كاليفورنيا
accredited the school after rigorous inspection,
اعتمد الكلية بعد تفتيش دقيق،
and the new physicians are making good
و الأطباء الجدد يبلون بلاءً حسناً
on Cuba's big bet,
في رهان كوبا الكبير،
passing their boards and accepted
يعبرون حدودهم و يُقبلون
into highly respected residencies
في أماكن الإقامة الأعلى احتراماً
from New York to Chicago to New Mexico.
من نيويورك لشيكاغو و حتى نيو ميكسيكو.
Two hundred strong, they're coming
مئتان من الأقوياء، إنهم عائدون
back to the United States energized,
للولايات المتحدة منشطين
and also dissatisfied.
و مستائين.
As one grad put it,
كما وضح أحد الخريجين،
in Cuba, "We are trained to provide quality care
في كوبا ,"تم تدريبنا لتقديم رعاية جيدة
with minimal resources,
بأقل الإمكانيات،
so when I see all the resources we have here,
لذا عندما أري كل الامكانيات المتاحة هنا،
and you tell me that's not possible,
و أنت تخبرني أنه ليس ممكناً،
I know it's not true.
أنا أعلم أن ذلك غير صحيح.
Not only have I seen it work, I've done the work."
ليس فقط أني رأيت هذا يعمل بالفعل، بل بقمت بفعله بنفسي."
ELAM's graduates,
خريجو ELAM،
some from right here in D.C. and Baltimore,
بعضهم من هنا، من ولاية واشنطن و بالتيمور،
have come from the poorest of the poor
قد أتوا من بين أفقر الفقراء
to offer health, education
لتقديم الرعاية الصحية و التعليم
and a voice to their communities.
و صوت لمجتمعاتهم.
They've done the heavy lifting.
لقد قاموا بالجهد الأكبر.
Now we need to do our part
يجب أن نقوم بدورنا الآن
to support the 23,000 and counting,
لدعم الـ 23 ألف و يزيد،
All of us —
كلنا -
foundations, residency directors, press,
المؤسسات و المسئولين عن الإقامات و الصحافة
entrepreneurs, policymakers, people —
و رجال الاعمال و صناع القرار و الناس -
need to step up.
يجب أن نخطو خطوة.
We need to do much more globally
نحتاج أن نقوم بالمزيد على الصعيد العالمي
to give these new doctors the opportunity
لإعطاء هؤلاء الاطباء المزيد من الفرص
to prove their mettle.
لإثبات حماسهم.
They need to be able
هم يحتاجون أن يتمكنوا
to take their countries' licensing exams.
من الحصول علي امتحانات رخصة مزاولة المهنة في بلادهم.
They need jobs in the public health sector
يحتاجون لوظائف في القطاع العام للصحة
or in nonprofit health centers
أو في مراكز الصحة الغير ربحية
to put their training and commitment to work.
ليضعوا تدريبهم و التزامهم في العمل.
They need the chance to be
يحتاجون الفرصة ليكونوا
the doctors their patients need.
الأطباء الذين يحتاجهم مرضاهم.
To move forward,
لنتقدم،
we may have to find our way back
ربما نحتاج لأن نعود
to that pediatrician who would
لطبيب الأطفال الذي
knock on my family's door
يطرق باب بيت عائلتي
on the South Side of Chicago when I was a kid,
في الجانب الجنوبي من شيكاغو عندما كنت طفلة،
who made house calls,
و الذي قام بالاتصال بالمنزل،
who was a public servant.
و الذي كان خادماً للعامة.
These aren't such new ideas
لا يوجد أفكار جديدة مثل هذه
of what medicine should be.
لكيف يجب أن يكون الطب.
What's new is the scaling up
الجديد هو العمل علي مقياس أكبر
and the faces of the doctors themselves:
و أوجه الأطباء أنفسهم:
an ELAM graduate is more likely to be a she
غالباً ما يكون خريج ELAM أنثي
than a he;
أكثر من ذكر؛
In the Amazon, Peru or Guatemala,
في الأمازون و بيرو أو غواتيمالا،
an indigenous doctor;
طبيبة من السكان الأصليين:
in the USA, a doctor of color
في أمريكا طبيبة ملونة
who speaks fluent Spanish.
تتكلم الإسبانية بطلاقة.
She is well trained, can be counted on,
هي مدربة جيداً، و يمكن الاعتماد عليها،
and shares the face and culture of her patients,
و تشارك وجه و ثقافة مرضاها،
and she deserves our support surely,
و تستحق دعمنا بالتأكيد،
because whether by subway, mule, or canoe,
لأنها سواء بقطارات الأنفاق أو بالحمار أو بالزورق،
she is teaching us to walk the walk.
هي تعلمنا أن نمشي الدرب.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً. (تصفيق)